General Manuscripts Miscellaneous Collection, 1502-2012: Finding Aid C0140
Manuscripts Division
- Williamson, George Charles, 1858-1942, 1916; 1 box (Box 54)
  TLS to M. Taylor Pyne, 8 April 1916. AM 12463
- Williamson, George Charles, 1858-1942, 1920; 1 box (Box 54)
  13 ALsS, 2 TLsS, and 1 TL to Austin Dobson, 13 August - 11 December 1920. AM 21566
- Willis, Anthony, Certificate of Freedom from the City and County of New York, 1811 April 26-27; Willis, Anthony, circa 1783-; 1 folder (Box B-001675, Folder 5)
  Consists of a certificate of freedom for Anthony Willis, an African American man living in New York City in the early 19th century. The certificate describes Willis as "a black man… about the age of twenty eight years, and was born at Suffolk County in the State of New York… about five feet six inches, has dark eyes and black hair." In this document, Peter Connor testifies that he has known Willis for two years, and that during that time Willis "hath been reputed and considered to be free, and hath continually acted as a free man during the said time, and that the said Anthony was born free." This statement is certified by judge and alderman Charles Dickinson.
  Purchased from Swann Auction Galleries (Sale 2562, Lot 22) in 2021 (AM 2022-013).
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Free African Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- 1775-1865 -- Sources; Free papers -- 19th century
- Willis, Nathaniel Parker, 1806-1867, undated; 1 box (Box 54)
  Autograph signature, n.d.; ALS to Robert Miller, n.d.; copy of autographed engraving, n.d. AM 17407
- Willis, Nathaniel Parker, 1806-1867, 1848-1857; 1 box (Box 54)
  5 ALsS to W. Ward, 1848-1857. AM 12669
- Willis, Nathaniel Parker, 1806-1867, 1849; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS to "Dear Sir," 7 March 1849. AM 83-52
- Willson, Augustus E., 1846-1931, 1910; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS to Logan C. Murray endorsing Burton Vance, 22 November 1910. AM 10626
- Wilkie, Wendell Lewis, 1892-1944, 1 box (Box 54)
  TLS to Mr. Davies, appreciation for his support, 23 May 1944. AM 16195
- Wilkinson, James, 1757-1825, 1799; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS to Hon. H. Glen of Schenectady, 4 September 1799. AM 90-60
- Wilson, Andrew Wilkins, 1890; 1 box (Box 54)
  Memoirs, TM (Xerox), 19 March 1890. AM 18783
- Wilson, Edith Bolling Galt, 1872-1961, 1924-1956; 1 box (Box 54)
  2 ALsS, 1 ANS, 1 TL (Carbon), and 1 CS, to and from various correspondents, 1924-1956. AM 20110
- Wilson, Francis, 1854-1935, 1925; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS to Mr. Frolich, thank-you note, 12 December 1925. AM 22077
- Wilson, Harry Leon, 1867-1939, 1915-1926; 1 box (Box 54)
  2 TLsS to W. C. Gibson, 18 October 1915 and 8 July 1924; ALS to Gibson, 26 August 1926; 4 snapshots of Wilson's children and 8 postcard photographs of the Bohemian Grave, n.d. AM 82-110
- Wilson, Henry, 1812-1875, 1848; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS to Edward L. Pierce, 2 October 1848. AM 9736
- Wilson, Jerome Nelson, Stereoview Photograph of Voters in Savannah, Georgia, 1868 November 3; Wilson, J. N. (Jerome Nelson), 1827-1897; 1 folder (Box B-001675, Folder 10)
  Consists of a stereoview photograph by Jermone Nelson Wilson (1827-1897), depicting Black and white voters in Savannah, Georgia, on Election Day in 1868, which was the first presidential election in which formerly enslaved people in the American South were able to participate. This photograph shows a crowd of Savannah voters lined up around a large banner for the Ulysses S. Grant ticket and includes handwritten captions reading "First Colored Vote" and "Election Scene." Many of the voters in the far distance appear to be Black, and at least one of the dozen men perched on fence posts in the foreground appears to be white.
  Purchased from Swann Auction Galleries (Sale 2562, Lot 334) in 2021 (AM 2022-013).
  African Americans -- Suffrage -- Georgia -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Presidents -- Election -- United States -- 1868; Savannah (Ga.) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; United States -- Politics and government -- History -- 1865-1869 -- Sources; Stereoscopic photographs -- 19th century
- Wilson, John, 1810; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS to James Vandervoort in NY describing a trip, 2 September 1810. AM 85-22
- Wilson, Keith, 1972; 1 box (Box 54)
  TLS to Alfred Bush concerning acquisition of his works by the Princeton Library, enclosing a ditto sheet of his publications, and announcing the publication of "The Old Man and Others," 23 November 1972.
- Wilson, Robert G, 1823; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS to William W. Woodward enclosing money, discussion of a new edition of "Scott's Life," 24 April 1823. AM 2008 Pyne Henry
- Wimbish, Lewis W. and Thomas Jeffreys, Memorandum of Agreement for Employment, 1873; 1 box (Box 54)
  Consists of a manuscript labor contract between Lewis W. Wimbish, a white Virginia landowner (likely in Mecklenburg County), and Thomas Jeffreys, an African American farm worker who was born in Virginia around 1837. Dating to the Reconstruction Era, this year-long contract specifies that Wimbish will pay Jeffreys sixty dollars for his services as a "farm hand and general laborer." The contract also states that Wimbish will furnish Jeffreys with a house and food ("three barrels of corn, one hundred and twenty five pounds of pork") and that Jeffreys will have one day per week to devote to the farming of his own crops. The contract is signed by both men (Jeffreys with an "X" mark), as well as by a witness (A.S. Lee).
  AM 2020-44
  Purchased from Between the Covers Rare Books in December 2019.
  African American farmers -- Virginia -- Economic conditions -- 19th century.; African Americans -- History -- 1863-1877 -- Sources.; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- Virginia.
- Wimbish, Samuel, Class of 1801, 1799; 1 box (Box 54)
  2 ALsS (Photostats) to his mother from Princeton, 1 July and 16 October 1799. AM 14374
- Wingate, Reginald, 1861-1953, 1916; 1 box (Box 54)
  L (copy) written as Governor-General of Sudan to Naum Bey in reply to his TLS (enclosed) of 7 May 1916, 16 May 1916. AM 15450
- Wingate, John, 1813; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALs to Gen. William Henry Harrison, relating to military matters, 25 March 1813. AM 80-76
- Winters, Yvor, 1900-1968, 1941; 1 box (Box 54)
  "On the Possibility of a Cooperative History of American Literature," TM, 1941. AM 12221
- Winthrop, John, 1588-1649, 1645; 1 box (Box 54)
  Photostats from Diary, 11 November to 5 December 1645.
- Winthrop, Robert Charles, 1809-1894, undated; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS to David A. Hall, relative to securing a house for the winter, n.d. AM 9304
- Winthrop, Robert Charles, 1809-1894, 1876-1878; 1 box (Box 54)
  6 ALsS to Edward L. Pierce about letters of Charles Sumner, 1876-1878. AM 9737-9742
- Winthrop, Robert Charles, 1809-1894, 1873; 1 box (Box 54)
  ANS to L. J. Cist, 28 January 1873. AM 12716
- Wistar Party, 1836; 1 box (Box 54)
  DS to Lewis B. Hunter, invitation from Dr. Robert Nare to attend the "Wistar Party," 1 December 1836. AM 9164
- Wister, Owen, 1860-1938, 1918; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS to Erastus Brainerd concerning Hearst and his writings, 5 February 1918. AM 11865
- Wister, Owen, 1860-1938, undated; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS to John Philadelphia, asking him to comment on a piece of writing, n.d. AM 13240
- Wister, Owen, 1860-1938, undated; 1 box (Box 54)
  ANS to "Sir," n.d. AM 15621
- Wister, Owen, 1860-1938, 1891-1938; 1 box (Box 54)
  CS from W. Geo. Weld, 7 August 1891; NS and 7 ALsS to Barklie Henry, 1891-1938; TL (Carbon) from Barklie Henry 28 June 1938. AM 79-73
- Wittick, Ben, Photograph of a Navajo Warrior and an African American Soldier, circa 1887; Wittick, Ben, 1845-1903; 1 folder (Box B-001559, Folder 14)
  Consists of an albumen photograph picturing a Navajo warrior and an African American soldier. Though uncredited and undated, the photograph was likely taken by Ben Wittick in Arizona Territory around 1887. The captions "Navajo Warrior" and "Negro Cavalry" have been inscribed in ink beneath each subject, and neither subject has been identified by their name.
  Wittick
  Ben Wittick (1845-1903) was an American photographer known for his photographs of landscapes, railroads, and Native American peoples in the American Southwest. Born in Pennsylvania, Wittick traveled westward in 1878 and initially worked for the Atlantic and Pacific Railroad, later establishing a studio in Gallup, New Mexico, and then Fort Wingate. Among his subjects were Apache, Navajo, and Zuni people; and landscapes of Canyon de Chelly and other scenes on the traditional lands of the Navajo and Pueblo peoples. He died from a rattlesnake bite in 1903.
  African American soldiers -- West (U.S.) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Navajo Indians -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Albumen prints
- Wolcott, B. Stuart, 1917; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS to Francis Charles MacDonald, telling of his experiences in aviation training in the World War, 10 August 1917. AM 10375
- Wolfe, Humbert, 1885-1940, 1926-1937; 1 box (Box 54)
  10 TLsS to H. W. Yoxall, 1926-1927; TLS to Miss F. Tennyson Jesse, 18 February 1937. AM 1999-67
- Wolfe, Thomas, 1900-1938, 1934-1939; 1 box
  - Wolfe, Thomas, 1900-1938, "Last Poem/Brooklyn" and Related Materials, 1934; 1 box (Box 54)
    "Last Poem/Brooklyn," TM, 1934; ALS from Elizabeth Lemon to Maxwell Perkins, n.d.; photograph of portrait of Wolfe by Douglas Gersline, n.d. AM 84-21
  - Wolfe, Thomas, 1900-1938, Photograph, 1939; 1 box (Box 54)
    Photograph, full length, inscribed on retro by Mabel Wheaton to Helen Landon, Christmas 1939. AM 89-11
  - Wolfe, Thomas, 1900-1938, Letters to Katherine Jackson and Related Letter by Katherine Jackson to Her Family, 1935-1936; 1 box (Box 54)
    AM 2017-54
    Consists of correspondence documenting Wolfe's relationship with his editors at Scribner's. Letters from Thomas Wolfe to Katherine Jackson include a four-page autograph letter sent from London on March 29, 1935, and a printed Christmas card with an undated autograph note. Jackson was an editor at Scribner's Magazine, working with Maxwell Perkins, and later at Harper's Magazine, where she wrote the "Books in Brief" column from 1944 to 1969. Her work placed her in contact with many prominent writers and scholars of the day, many of whom she befriended, including Thomas Wolfe. In his March 1935 letter, Wolfe describes feeling isolated from America, a restless night in Paris, and his upcoming plans to travel to Denmark and Russia. He also requests information from Jackson about his forthcoming book, Of Time and the River. Also present is a carbon copy of a letter Jackson wrote to her parents on January 3, 1936, describing a road bump in her friendship with Wolfe after Jackson told Wolfe that it was not prudent to publish stories in magazines as opposed to books, causing a stir between Wolfe and editor Max Perkins, who later diffused the conflict.
- Wolff, Albert, 1884-1970, 1919-1920; 1 box (Box 54)
  ALS, unaddressed, 9 November 1919; ALS, unaddressed, in French, 1920. AM 2002-135
- Wolfgang, Wilhelm, Count Palatine du Rhin, 1609; 1 box (Box 54)
  LS to King, in French, on military matters, 15 November 1609. AM 14564
- Wong, Anna May, 1905-1961, undated; 1 box (Box 58)
  8 by 18 in. ink and watercolor drawing. AM 2004-167
- Wood, Grant, 1891-1942, 1929-1983; 1 box (Box 55)
  Photographs and newspaper clippings concerning Wood, 1929-1983. AM 87-115
- Wood, John George, 1827-1889, 1887; 1 box (Box 55)
  ALS to "Dear Madam," in regard to his lecture on the horse to be given in Carlisle, 22 December 1887. AM 13257
- Wood, L. F., Sharecropping Agreement with Fifteen Freedmen and Freedwomen on the Mount Hope Plantation, Mississippi, 1865 May 25-August 23; 1 box (Box P-000109)
  Consists of a sharecropping agreement between L. F. Wood of the Mount Hope Plantation in Jefferson County, Mississippi, and fifteen freedmen and freedwomen. The contract is signed by Wood, two witnesses, and the freedmen and freedwomen by mark and dated May 25, 1865. Names listed include Isham Bass (46), Robert Bass (15), Richard Thompson (46), Eliza Thompson (45), Daniel Thompson (15), Emeline Darnald (38), Hager Curtis (52), Prince Miller (17), Minda Miller (28), Rachel Williams (46), Matilda Fitzgerald (21), Edward Johnson (40), Hester Johnson (30), Cornelia Griffin (18), and Perry Christmas (19).
  In this document, signed weeks after the close of the American Civil War, these laborers agree to work as sharecroppers on the plantation on which they were formerly enslaved for 10 hours per day, 5 days per week, for the remainder of the year. The plantation owner agrees to "furnish the said freedmen with food & clothes to the extent of my means, also to allow said freedmen the use of teams & plantation utensils to cultivate their respective crops." Each freedman and freedwoman is also given "one to three acres of land to cultivate on his or her own account."
  The terms of this agreement were enforced by Union troops; the docketing on verso is signed by the county's lieutenant and sub-commander of freedmen, who certified to "the within contract being in conformity to Gen. Order No. 34." A tax of $33 was noted as paid through August 23 on eleven remaining "hands."
  AM 2018-103
  African Americans -- Mississippi -- Economic conditions -- 19th century -- Sources; Freed persons -- Mississippi -- Jefferson County -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Sharecroppers -- Southern States -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.
- Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927, 1917; 1 box (Box 55)
  TLS to Governor Morris, advising entering the war as soon as possible, 9 April 1917. AM 11453
- Wood Works Press, Broadside of "Touch Me" by Stanley Kunitz, 2000-2002; Kunitz, Stanley, 1905-2006.; Wood Works (Press); 1 folder (Box B-001621, Folder 7)
  Gift of Carol Blinn in 2020 (AM 2022-029).
  Signed by Stanley Kunitz. 109/190.
  Kunitz, Stanley, 1905-2006.
  Stanley Kunitz was born on July 29, 1905, in Worcester, Massachusetts. His parents, Yetta Helen and Solomon Z. Kunitz, both Eastern European immigrants, owned and operated a dress manufacturing company in Worcester. After graduating from Classical High School, Kunitz left Worcester to attend Harvard University. In 1926 he received his bachelor's degree with highest honors and was also awarded the Garrison Medal for Poetry by the University. Kunitz remained in Cambridge to earn a master's degree, which he completed in 1927. At this time, Kunitz returned to Worcester, where he worked as a feature reporter for the daily newspaper, The Worcester Telegram; however, Kunitz grew weary of his hometown rather quickly and so left for New York City in 1928 in search of more interesting prospects.
  In New York City Kunitz secured a position at the H. W. Wilson Company, where he edited, either alone or collaboratively, seven reference works of literary biography and the Wilson Library Bulletin. Kunitz's first H. W. Wilson book, Living Authors: A Book of Biographies, was published in 1931 under the pseudonym "Dilly Tante," and his final Wilson book, European Authors, 1000-1900, was published in 1967. The H. W. Wilson Company offered Kunitz a great deal of freedom to pursue his literary interests. For instance, Kunitz was permitted to go abroad in 1929-1930, during which time he polished the poems (and worked on an unfinished novel) that would become, upon his return from Europe in 1930, his first published book of verse, Intellectual Things. Kunitz was also able to maintain his position at H. W. Wilson despite having relocated from New York City to a farm in Mansfield Center, Connecticut around 1931 with his first wife, Helen Pearce (married 1930-1937).
  Although Kunitz continued to edit reference books for H. W. Wilson Company through the 1960s, he relinquished his position in 1943 when he was drafted into the U. S. Army. Initially Kunitz petitioned to be classified as a conscientious objector, but the Army denied his request, forcing Kunitz to serve in the military with the Air Transport Command for the duration of the war. During his enlistment, Kunitz published his second book of poetry, Passport to the War (1944), which was inspired by his wartime experiences.
  After his release from the service in 1945, Kunitz lived briefly in Santa Fe, New Mexico, and then accepted his first teaching position at Bennington College in 1946. This was to be the first of many such positions for Kunitz, who continued to teach through the 1980s but remained determined to put writing before teaching, never accepting a tenure-track faculty position. He left Bennington College precipitously in 1949 after a dispute with an administrator and took a position at Potsdam State College (now SUNY College at Potsdam), Potsdam, New York, as the curriculum advisor to the English Department. Here, he also taught summer workshops from 1949 to 1953. During this brief (1949-1950) stay in Potsdam, Kunitz's second wife, Eleanor Evans (married 1939-1958) gave birth to their daughter, Gretchen.
  In 1950 Kunitz again found himself in New York City, where he held numerous teaching positions at various universities, colleges, and institutions, including The New School for Social Research (1950-1957), the Poetry Center of the 92nd Street YM-YWHA (1958-1962), Queens College (1956-1957), and Columbia University as a lecturer (1963-1966) and then as an adjunct professor of writing (1967-1985). He also held teaching positions further afield in such places as the University of Washington, where he was the poet-in-residence (1955-1956), Brandeis University (1958-1959), Yale University (1971, fellow since 1969), Rutgers University (1974), and Princeton University (1978-1979). In 1958 he married the painter and poet Elise Asher (1912-2004), with whom he spent the rest of his life.
  Aside from teaching, Kunitz was an active member of the greater literary community. In 1968 he helped found the Fine Arts Work Center, an artists' colony in Provincetown, Massachusetts, and continued to be a stalwart supporter of the Center, evident in his service on the Board of Trustees, the Executive Committee, and the writing division. As the editor of the Yale Series of Younger Poets from 1969 to 1977, Kunitz gave rise to a new generation of poets, including such well-known poets as Carolyn Forché and Michael Ryan. Kunitz was also a member of the Academy of American Poets and the American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters. He served as the Poetry Consultant for the Library of Congress (1974-1976) and, along with Elizabeth Kray, founded Poets House in New York City in 1985. At the age of 95 Kunitz was named U.S. Poet Laureate, a post he served for two years (2000-2001). Internationally Kunitz participated in a number of cultural exchange programs, which included trips to Russia and Poland in 1967, to Senegal and Ghana in 1976, to Russia again in 1979, and to Israel and Egypt in 1980.
  Kunitz's other publications include Selected Poems, 1928-1958 (1959), for which he received the Pulitzer Prize in 1959, The Testing-Tree (1971), The Terrible Threshold (1974), The Poems of Stanley Kunitz: 1928-1978 (1979), Next-to-Last Things (1985), and Passing Through (1995), for which he received the 1995 National Book Award, The Collected Poems of Stanley Kunitz (2000) and The Wild Braid (2005), a book he co-wrote with Genine Lentine. In 1975 Kunitz published a book of prose entitled A Kind of Order, A Kind of Folly. He edited The Poems of John Keats (1964) and The Essential Blake (1987). In addition Kunitz has also been involved in translating poetry into English. He collaborated with Max Hayward on Poems of Akhamatova (1973) and, with others, translated Andrei Voznesenskii's Story under Full Sail (1974). In 1978 he edited and co-translated the Ukrainian poet Ivan Drach's Orchard Lamps.
  In addition to the Pulitzer Prize and the National Book Award, Kunitz won other prestigious awards, which include a John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Fellowship (1945-1946), National Institute of Arts and Letters Award (1959), Academy of American Poets fellowship (1968), National Endowment for the Arts senior fellowship (1984), Bollingen Prize in Poetry, Yale University Library (1987), and the National Medal of Arts (1993).
  Equally lauded for his talents as a gardener, Kunitz's Provincetown, MA home featured a sprawling, multi-tiered garden that he had coaxed from sand. His final book, The Wild Braid: A Poet Reflects on a Century in the Garden (2005), co-written with Genine Lentine, reveals the interconnectedness of his writing and gardening habits. A few months shy of his 101th birthday, Stanley Kunitz died at his home in New York City.
  American poetry -- 20th century.; Broadsides (notices)
- Woodbury, Levi, 1789-1851, 1832-1847; 1 box (Box 55)
  ALS to Samuel Smith (Senator), 11 June 1832; DS to S. Swaitwood, 27 August 1855; ALS to Caleb Stark, 16 March 1839; ALS to Robert J. Walker, 9 April 1847; 4 engravings of Woodbury, n.d. AM 15061, 18565
- Woods, Richard Flavel, Class of 1892, undated; 1 box (Box 55)
  4 drawings and 1 watercolor, landscapes, n.d. AM 15952
- Woods, William Burnham, 1824-1887, 1879-1884; 1 box (Box 55)
  LS and ALS to Charles Devens, 8 March 1879 and 28 March 1877; ANS to Col. Jones, 6 August 1884; 2 engravings of Woods, n.d. AM 18565
- Woodward, Arthur Smith, 1864-1944, 1932; 1 box (Box 55)
  ALS to W. B. Scott, expressing appreciation for his work, May 1932. AM 12513
- Woolf, Virginia, 1882-1941, 1 box (Box 55)
  TLS to Miss Cooley thanking her for her support, 9 February 1941. AM 15711
- Woollcott, Alexander, 1887-1943, 1934-1946; 1 box (Box 55)
  TNS and ANS to Carl T. Naumburg, 1934 and 1937; TNS by L. Robins to Naumburg, 1946. AM 1993-121
- Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892, 1860-1882; 1 box (Box 55)
  14 ALsS to various correspondents, 1860-1882. AM 17773, 19483
- Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892, 1875-1883; 1 box (Box 55)
  ALS to "Sir," 7 September 1875; ALs to "My dear Faithful," 4 January 1883. AM 19865
- Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892, 1864; 1 box (Box 55)
  ALS to Christina Georgina Rossetti, 25 May 1864. AM 19862
- Woolsey, Sarah Chauncey, 1835-1905, undated; 1 box (Box 55)
  ALS to Miss Booth, letter of condolence, n.d. AM 80-79
- Woolson, Constance Fenimore, 1840-1894, 1891; 1 box (Box 55)
  ALS to Mary L. Booth asking that her name not appear with an article, 2 February 1891. AM 80-79
- Woolverton, Joan, 1903; 1 box (Box 58)
  19 by 30 in. genealogical registers, 1903. AM 17099
- Worcester, J. E, 1860-1893; 1 box (Box 55)
  ALS to "Dear Sir," regarding errors in Funk and Wagnall's dictionary, 30 November 1860; signature of Funk, 25 December 1893. AM 12456
- Wordin, Helen "Nellie" Caroline, Diary, 1858-1893; Wordin, Helen Caroline, 1842-; 1 folder (Box B-001552, Folder 3)
  Consists of a manuscript diary spanning forty-five years in the life of Helen "Nellie" Caroline Wordin (1842- ), an educated, single white woman living in Bridgeport, Connecticut, in the 19th century who attended school in Petersburg, Virginia, during the outbreak of the American Civil War.